soft engine radio episode 136 past
present and future of model-driven
architecture with david frankel this is
software engineering radio the podcast
for professional developers on the web
at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website possible
[Music]
welcome everyone to a new episode of the
software engineering radio my name is
doc Lila
I'm your host today straight from the
Silicon Valley as a kind of subsidiary
for the software engineering radio it's
my first show you can learn about me at
dub dub dub of a dog rie achieved arc
but my guest today is david frankel a
colleague at sa p labs here in the
Silicon Valley hi Dave hi
glad to have you thanks I really
appreciate the opportunity to talk here
hmm
our topic today is a model driven
architecture past present and future
we'll be taking both somewhat broader a
sweep and that previous episode have
done and we'll also be talking about
david's long tenure on the subject as
well as his most recent recent thoughts
and activities um I noticed it was
actually fun to see your a colleague
here and I could interview you for MBA
we first met I believe UBS and Zurich
over ten years ago when you were doing
some of the earlier MDA projects one
might say that actually won a prize I
remember the was the global business
object project right you remember that
great sure oh yeah there was a
translator hiding in the UVA yeah
exactly
those were the heydays of Cobra this
cover already MDA a level of work well
it's interesting what happened with
carbide I don't normally associate
corporate directly with MDA except that
they both come out of the yeonji so
there is a connection core but just in
terms of what happened with CORBA it if
you're an enterprise computer and karma
appears to have died it is there's
certain parts of core core bot
the core security the corporate
transaction service and IOP are buried
deep in the plumbing of J of Java
Enterprise and actually you have to have
those to get certification for Java
Enterprise but but core by an enterprise
computing core go boss the battle of the
programming model to Java to do so the
programming model that surfaces to the
programmer is how we name a programming
model
nothing of course then CORBA lost that
battle however in embedded in real time
services it's very much alive they go to
the OMG today this sort of its kind of
day of quarterly meetings and there's
just no about 250-300 people come and
there's a lot of activity both in both
in the MDA stack and in the corpus stack
the corpus stack it's all real-time
embedded systems people that are
involved in that and it's very much
alive there you take a company like
Tolly so big you know the big
engineering firm and except probably has
about 75,000 people based in France's
with strong presence all over Western
Europe they have very deep commitment to
MDA they've rolled out from their
central architecture group in Paris a
few years ago and commitment to none but
MDA and Corbeau they use the corporate
component model as their run time so
they have MVA they have run today of md
8 the easy MDA stack for their modeling
tools and and they have a lot of code
generation or model execution and their
their execution platform is corbett
component model which is also known as
court with three okay so the background
of my question was the thought that
Kaba tried to establish service
architectures and i thought or maybe you
can help me clarify that what's the
connection between the attempt to
modernize traditional software systems
with service architectures well defined
services and interactions and MDA yeah
well so if you want to put Corbin that
in you know analyze corporate from that
perspective and
than the NDA Sakura actually when people
when it was initially being warped on in
the first part of the 90s the vision
that people were talking about was very
very similar to what people talk about
with service-oriented architecture you
know the first major book that was
written about carp probably was it
wasn't a very technical book that was
written by Mike I was called object
technology revolution written by Mike
Guttman and who's one of the original
authors of ILP and they're calling and
Jason Matthews right and if you read
that book the vision they lay out is the
same vision that people are laying out
you know loosely coupled services with
you know that they just thought Cobra
was going to be the technical mechanism
for describing these interfaces and well
you know really what happened was core
but for various reasons and the core
ball was not broadly adopted Microsoft
resisted adopting carbon they went the
wrong way you know with common and decom
and there was always this split and
today with it with soy that's based on
your web services yes the vision is
basically the same and technically in a
sense like they'll be building this web
services stack to kind of rebuild a
stack it's art it's debatable whether it
was rebuilt in a more efficient way than
if it wasn't with the corpus stack
however the real difference is not
technical but it's it's the fact that we
had broadened with a broad industry
adoption that Microsoft was on board you
know all the all that come everybody was
on board and that makes it that's a very
substantial difference you know that
that really and and that's why it's got
me you know it's gotten more broader
it's getting broader adoption and core
ends up sort of often a niche in the
real-time embedded systems yeah you mean
you're making an important point that I
wanted to come talk to still let me just
ask were there any lessons to be learned
from Kaba about things that didn't work
too well but that had an influence on
how later and
technology stacks from loans yeah yeah
one of the things was that for well
there's two things first of all Corbeau
the definition of a Corbin interface is
a purely syntactical thing absolutely
straight syntax it gives you the
signature of the operations in the
interface there is no attempt whatsoever
to capture any kind of semantic content
now one could argue that okay you know
there's a separation of concerns maybe
that's just about the syntax okay fine
and you put this anything somewhere else
but the where to put the somewhere the
semantics in a machine readable form was
never really addressed that that was one
problem the second problem was as Java
as it became clear that corporate was
not going to be the only distributed the
only platform the strip for this should
be the computing you really have to
think about well you know can we do you
know raising the level of abstraction
another well I mean you have to have
something that you could you could do
specifications where you would that
would be free of having to be forced at
that point to make the choice between
korva or java enterprise or something
else and so that got us thinking that
you know well this is the reality what's
going on in the industry and and then
you know you had to and there was some
of this then at the same time there was
the modeling the stuff was going on in
the modeling world so Carver was it's a
textual you know IDL interface
description language is a purely textual
there's really no modeling like no
visual language in Europe this is the
time of visual modeling languages were
rising object-oriented okay so there was
sort of another part of the
object-oriented camp was this modeling
camp and you had the three camps you
know you had rows you know you had great
boots she had Jim Rome Talia Jacobson
you know they were all well you know
like with around 97 they've all come
together the three of them for you mean
amigos and OMG gets the rights to you
know yeah and that was the first thing
that she ever had that was not corporate
based and that was controversial inside
inside of me oMG
Tim why are we getting into something
that's not karva yeah and so the
argument the counter argument was well
look you know it's evident that there's
going to be more than one distributed
object computing platform and we need
and also we don't you know we're the
object management group we've neglected
the object may be infected the modeling
side you know so that argument one the
day and also from a semantics
perspective because that's not exactly
your strong suit well it's funny because
you know the human has has more
capability to model semantics than
people realize but it's Cato's
capabilities are typically not used if
you look at the typical uml model that
you know somebody in an IT
you know organization for some project
produces I would say that those models
really when you come down toward are
purely syntactical you know they're
defining classes with upper right you
know with attributes and operations and
it's just it's not that much different
than that idea of interface it's just
with its pictures right then they have
slightly different rules as an idea but
plus they have okay they have other
dimensions they have to sequence
diagrams and the state diagrams all that
other stuff and so with that you can put
the class diagrams that themselves are
purely syntactic wrong you can start to
get at some of the semantics of the
operations you can model them and with
with you my other state you know there
state machines you can model the then
through activity modeling but the the
client is there's an awful lot of class
modeling that goes on in UML and that
does not take advantage of the fact that
the UML has the object constraint
language ocl now it's a first-order
predicate lot logic and it allows you to
specify invariant rules and
preconditions and postconditions for
your operations in terms of your
structural information model in a way
that is mathematically precise even
though you can your models can be at a
very high level of abstraction that
begins to you start to get at more
semantics I mean a lot of ocl
particularly the invariant rules you
know are sort of ruling out corner cases
but some of it you know like you would
froggy in other word they would fall
under the category more of like a well
form this world but a lot of it is you
start to get moving area of business
rules like if this okay if you know the
value of this of a part of the portfolio
is more than a million dollars then if
this and if the date you know is after
July 15th and this flag over here
whether this letter was sent to the
regulatory authority is is false you've
got a problem right okay so that's what
you're saying you can actually do some
behavioral auditing yeah or more
precisely semantics and with the you can
actually do some people behavioral
modeling with the pre and post a
particularly the post conditions because
with the post conditions you can say
we'll just take a typical an operation
that you might have in a business system
like to roll over and the end of month
receivables roll over you know you roll
over current 30 days and 30 to 60 etc
you can specify that you know you can
specify that behavior in LCL so I
already see we have a long list of
topics and we are drawing you're really
on your
because tremendous breadth and depth of
experience but I didn't do in the
beginning and listeners probably got an
initial glance at it from from the
website but maybe you want to shortly
talk about your own in this because I
remember listening to you at ETH Zurich
and talk about the core component model
for example yeah I don't want to go back
yet too much to cover yet but you've
definitely been involved in some of
these standardization efforts and maybe
you want to talk about what you did in
that respect in the corporate component
mode starting there yeah okay
well I was involved in the team that
specified the corporate component model
and we were trying to go I mean it was a
big step beyond the basic core ba
because it gave us a model for you could
say you know you could model a component
that provided and required interfaces it
could provide multiple interfaces
require multiple interfaces and you
could and then add the notion of
assemblies where you could take these
you can plug a requirement for making we
call them parts required parts and use
it sports yeah and you can take these
I'm sorry the requirement parts and
provide support systems but you could
take these and you can use them as the
basis or wiring components together and
assembly so now you have you create a
larger component for an application that
is an assembly of these components it
was a much more advanced model than EJB
actually knew zjb did not have that it
had they basically covered everything
ejv covered but it had this whole notion
of requiring and users ports which AJ
didn't have this so which gave you a
much a much more powerful assembly but
yeah we talked earlier before we started
the podcast about song and Garland's
welcome soft architecture so that sounds
the core component model as you
described it sounds pretty much like an
architectural description language is
that's MVA level work or
cursor or should MBA have that or not
you know it's really a different
dimension
well I to me I mean that the over
running from MDA is raising the level of
abstraction and how we develop software
MDA in one sense is a brand it's a
corporate it's I mean it's an OMG brand
they have it's a registered trademark
you know and there's a stack of you know
um LX and ly certain technologies you
know what sort of more sort of
philosophically model driven systems in
general as an effort to raise the level
of abstraction now Corbett did that to
some extent I mean it raised the level
for its day and raise the level of
abstraction above the programming
language because there and there and
there were programming language bindings
right and so you could you could specify
an interface where you can specify a
component and it was independent of
whether there was going to be an
implementation in CORBA or Java and in
fact the client and that you could have
a client and a server that one was in
one the client might have been accessing
the component and the client might be
written in Java the server might be
written in C++ and it you know you could
do that so they were raising the level
of abstraction above the programming
language above the operating system and
in a sense MDA was just the next step it
raised it above the distributed object
computing platform and these notions of
provides and required component of even
create the required components are just
ways to the you just give you new tools
to be able to you don't have to write
the as quite as much low-level code to
connect these things because the
language bindings for the core component
model provided a lot of the mechanics of
how you'd have to hook these things
together right so if that's but you know
there was an evolution well the way I
look at it
there was an evolution going on at that
point in time would you say the late 90s
by then we had already right essentially
we're doing already model driven the
development on the front ends of our
systems and on the back end you think
about it talk let's take take the back
end who is programming you know B plus
trees alone in low-level code to do an
enterprise application in the late 90s
by then you're using database management
systems you you would create a data
model schema you'd feed it into the
database management system it would do
all the heavy lifting yes you do some
fine tuning with triggers and stored
procedures and stuff like that but you
know most of the heavy lifting was done
by the by the database management system
using the data model right front end the
last time I wrote a C++ you know message
loop for Windows was when I discovered
Microsoft foundation classes and you
know that's a lot about you know 1994
and you know Microsoft foundation
classes what they allowed you to do and
UI development is very much like this
today okay you create you didn't create
your user and fit your dialog you paint
it whether what you see is what you get
a dialog editor you push a button that
generates a bunch of code there's places
where you add you have to add all the
you know UI event handlers so you're
saying this is all different
technologies but kind of inspired by the
idea of increasing that I'm not
expecting to be modern driven we were
already doing it in the front ends and
the back ends of the systems and what
you start seeing with Corp with CORBA
and the efforts with MCA is really about
was completely was sort of getting the
mid tiers as we're starting to develop
mid tier systems with web-based things
and you know distributed computing oh
yeah coping risks they have to automate
to have it all yeah can you but still
you've given us examples now and maybe
to clarify what what would you say is
essential about and
is that can you define an absolute terms
are that always a relative movement
toward smaller levels of abstraction now
the way I've tried to introduce it is
really with a theory of permanent
revolution you know ideally the yeah we
we're always looking for ways to be the
holy grail is you specified this is
behavior of your system and then
executes right we're not really there
but you know we there are certain ways
in which we're getting closer to that
and there's a and so that's really what
we're after
yet that sort of like they were asking
me we will asymptotically approach that
you know when even as Antonio might be
too optimistic but we're gradually we
raise that level yeah well that's a
funnel for coming to a fundamental
question which is programming and
modeling something very different or not
because if all you do is in both cases
so you are specifying in some form you
might argue that programming is just
modeling with abstractions programming
abstractions that are just not as high
level as you wish but programmers
typically would say yeah the morning
abstractions are just not complete and
consistent and orthogonal enough to
actually give me the power to be
complete such that it runs out of the
box so how bout you well I think that
the line between programming and
modeling is or is somewhat fuzzy okay
because in you know you're always
operating it's um you know some level of
abstraction above what's really going on
and you know we've gone from yeah it was
like Makoti and ones and zeros to
assemblers to compile you know I mean
third generation languages so I think
that if you really want to get
intellectually rigorous of it it gets
pretty hard to define the difference I
think you make a really important point
about one of the things that turns IT
people off to what they see in modeling
with what's called the modeling world
and that's the imprecision of it
you know yeah there there is a role
there is a role for casual modeling
let's say or informal modeling but you
know there also is an important role for
making any with with something like you
amount you're oftentimes see models that
though one of the attributes will have a
tie it's it'll be of a certain type but
the types not to find anywhere I'll just
call it date but you need to find your
day type anywhere right or the other
part of it is they don't use the ability
to specify any the constraints okay so
it's all very it's loose its imprecise
and developers look at that and they
they're they say this is fluff you know
how's this gonna help me yeah okay yeah
maybe this helps me a little bit
visualize the one I'm supposed to do but
that it you know now on the other hand
when you introduce the methodologies of
using these modeling languages with real
precision thinking about what is
computationally completed that level of
abstraction and they start to introduce
I find when I start tend to do something
yeah you can use these constraint
languages and and and you can generate
your je units out of that later you
could represent it starts to change in
terms of the debate when they can see
that a it is really rigorous and B that
it can even actually help them get their
work done because it saves them and I
oftentimes do go back to say to step
back of it you know when you do it you
know there's a lot of code generation
you're already raising a level of
abstraction you know in many ways you
don't do the eg of a object class you
don't write that by hand that's
generated by there by the application
server right yeah okay so so but in my
mind this raises the question that it's
almost also social problem because you
have architects doing UML and
programmers having to implement it in
Java or fix up holes and generate a
Travis Gallatin code and if only
programmers
is this distinction between architect
and programmer that we are trying to
establish we are not even there yet but
it seems to be a goal of the industry to
have these roles more precisely become
defined then then the architects tool
just does not deliver yet what the
Builder or the programmer needs a lot of
it is about to it for sure now there are
some tools out there that do that do
pretty interesting things and we'll win
the sir for certain classes of
applications you know within their their
world their sphere that they're
attacking will do a pretty good job and
one of the problems one of the problems
is a lot of the early tools try to
really attack the whole universe in
other words they were very opposite of
domain-specific they were just trying to
come up with their cogeneration
formulations to handle all kinds of
applications and that's a really
difficult problem and you know really
you need to if you're going to use you
amount you need to profile it to the
domain you're working with and you need
to write if you're going to do
cogeneration you need to write code
generators that are understand your your
UML profile that for most industrial
spoke for industrial scale applications
if you don't do that it's very hard to
do to do it without that's interesting I
never thought about it so in my mind you
have if you're programming you have your
java ide and you expect that to be
completely supporting what you have the
language all its features and then a
host of tools that somehow make it
easier to cope with a language like Java
so you're saying for UML we don't just
need a UML IDE that can cope with all
the UML features but rather you would
pare it down or say you really get very
selective use depending on your job
what's emerging the the kind of generic
UML tools are seeing today implement the
you know profiling mechanism so you know
you know was architected from the
beginning
the architects never expected that it
would be sufficient in and of itself for
industrial applications out of the box
they gave it extension mechanisms which
you used to build you know profiles for
example
uol doesn't know it out of the box give
you away
to model security to model quality of
service I can go on there's lots of
things or you know specific things about
certain domains so there yeah yeah
you're not talking well you're both
talking it seems to me about functional
and specific application domains and
some functional domains a lot of
functional requirements like security
and but on the other hand also extending
the modeling obstructions so the
libraries on the one hand so like how to
address security with the specific
implementation technology but also
high-level abstractions that are just
not there it's a good point there isn't
there's a net there's an architectural
engineering trade-off between how much
of the knowledge of the domain do you
put in reusable components and how much
of you put it in put in your design of a
domain-specific dialect and a compiler
or interpreter that understands that and
those have so you know there's there's
there's trade-offs there and so what you
see is people creating libraries of
components and then they create a URL
profile and then they create a these
tools all have the ability to plug in
they have FP as you plug in your your
code generator to cut the generated code
calls you into your library of
components
now there's interesting architectural
trade-off so how much you put in what
space no and you allow it by the way was
as far as MDA goes um Elmo's never
expected to can't be able to handle all
modeling so the core of MZ is really the
meta object facility model which is the
meta modeling language and UML is
defined in mauve and there are other
meta models that theology but there's a
lots of you know profiles that are being
used either proprietary ones being used
in industry and also there ones that
have been standardizing yeongji there's
one for software radio there
one for specifically for real-time
systems there's all kinds of things yeah
okay yes so I know the following
architecture pretty well when when I
worked with that profiles were really
barely doable was the existing tools
actually the way we did domain-specific
language this was literally as a
extension of you about taking as an
object onto framework on creating
subclasses and coping with all of that
yeah well I had one more question in
this space which is to hear your
thoughts on the idea of refinement I
remember way back probably by now the
Suzanne Mills they had a methodology
called catalysis which was trying to
bridge between programming and more
abstract architecture modeling I'm a
level modelling by saying it's all
really just a refinement process and by
that they tried to bring in precision
and and basically bridge that gap
between architect and hand by the
architect and code slaying developer
basically not does that fly is that
still a guiding metaphor the notion of
refinement or what are your thoughts
well to some extent yes but it really
you really have to have tooling that
manages it for you and if you don't have
tooling that that does a really good job
of managing the different levels it
breaks down really quickly okay that's
a--that's a big problem now in the
tooling area I'll say this
compared with five years ago we're in
much better shape the gyro mounted the
new crop of UML tools for UML 2.0 much
better than what we had five years ago
the profiling mechanisms are properly
implemented it is much better but in
terms of the tools being really
intelligent about managing the levels of
abstraction for you your your your for
the most part you're still on your own
you have to you have to build in you'd
have to do a lot of work with api's and
you know your billing using the AJ so
you know where there are some niche
tools that do that sir in certain niche
areas but but we have to so we've made
progress but there's there's room so
there's definitely room to go by the way
there was always a big debate and this
disrupted as a big debate in it cake
became very religious debate about you
know when the Microsoft folks Mike Mike
good colleagues of mine I go right who I
know and respect very much work their
software factories book today you know
Jack I mean field and Steve cook and
those guys you know they they came
forward with a philosophy that very very
strongly was in favor of multiple
round-trip engineering at multiple
levels and multiple levels of
abstraction where you could do anything
that you could do with the model of and
you could do in the code and it would be
reflected back up go to reflect down
were there there are strong religious
opinions about that kinds if you go to
Steve Miller like you know Slayer Miller
he's religious on the opposite pole you
know pure foreign engineering you know
you put even the imperative imperative
code is an abstract action language in
the UML model and you fight it's all for
regeneration you do not touch the
generated code yeah you know and then
there's there's a high group of hybrid
approaches in between so you know
they're now the if you do it all forward
engineering you don't have that problem
yeah I was about to say so it's all
about the impedance mismatch right
did anyone in your opinion win our where
the level of forward engineering
actually works I mean I don't look at
assembly one code any longer when I
program because I don't have to so on
that level its translation and it's just
fine but not every level is there yet
and then and then well first of all I
mean the Schreyer Beller approach in
which they way when UML came around they
migrated it in UML I mean they've for a
decade I mean decades they've been doing
very serious industrial works on
embedded systems you know like but you
know I mean switch you know talk to me
the case of switch boxes with you know
millions of lines of code all generated
through these act you know these these
things I mean that that stuff has been
in in in the embedded systems world
their way they were given way ahead of
enterprise computing in that some would
argue because and I tend to agree with
this although Steve Steve Mello I think
would challenge me but I tend to think
that in enterprise systems you're
dealing with so much legacy stuff it's
just things aren't as normalized and it
says harder to it's harder to do now you
the hybrid models I mean are great you
know one of them is okay so you talked
about well you know I don't look at the
assembly code that my compiler generates
so I'm old enough to remember you know
some of the early days when I was doing
C programming you could do things like
you could you you we would do could
hints to say to the compiler put this
variable on a register okay or we could
even drop down into it you could
actually being bad assembly code but
they hints to the register you know we
could sort of parameterizing we can do
you can still do that if you're gonna
take things like how something is
supposed to be mapped in a relational
database rather than making a
transparent so all kinds of never
sniffing where you somehow need to help
the underlying raw so that a year of
transparency it's it's slowly it's a
continuum
yeah so I'd be curious we already had
touched all
the cob of us-ascii combos I don't want
to go there again but the important
lesson of course was in terms of
industry impact you need to get all the
relevant players on board so Microsoft
does was back then Nepal's opposing
Cobra and had its own component model
become a distributor calm and then
distributed calm and so but that has
changed so was the new web services what
kind of how's that related to MDA is
that just yet another technology stack
that you can kind of look at from from
an MDA perspective to consider all the
modeling techniques or Vista and all
that out of MBA ignoring for where the
call of the OMG trademark actually it
turns out that when we look at where the
low-hanging fruit for modeling where the
growth in modeling model driven
approaches has occurred in the last
several years it's actually occurred in
that service-oriented area where the
you're not generating an application
what you're generating is the glue code
that that orchestrates the invocation of
services and it may not be fooling or
Eliza's web services although that says
yeah and and that that turns out to be
look that's a less difficult problem
than generating all your business logic
you know and that's a and and that turns
out to be a it had been one of the one
of the piece one of the things that was
lowest hanging on the tree and I there
was actually wrote an article about this
and business process trends maybe about
a year ago because I read a study I
think was IDC had done a study about
where the growth and knowledge of the
systems had occurred and they were
analyzing it and that was one of their
findings and I thought that was really
really pretty interesting and well
that's the same old story of escala it's
like making different types of
components from different software
sources basically making the
heterogeneous well water
quiet cooperation work together right so
you know it's still you know these these
these components that have the
service-oriented interfaces on them or
largely still being hand coded but the
orchestration you know you know modeling
that and generating the glue that's
that's all overhanging that's of just a
yellow hanging all these components were
hand coded because that's how they
started off not necessarily because
they're taking a motor-driven approach
would have been the wrong thing or just
maybe the growl of different approach
would have been the right thing that it
wasn't considered I mean you know
there's many many reasons yeah okay so
does that imply that model-driven
architecture motor-driven development is
something for legacy systems it just
implies it was one of the easiest
problems to apply to apply this to okay
oh yeah
that's way things tend to happen and we
tend to find the passive you know where
where the real economic return is fast
the way will you get the quote the
fastest time to value let's just put it
that way that's how I see it you also
see this now that's evolving to you know
the notion of executable business
process models which is sort of a sort
of in a sense a element of that you know
because you model and and now you start
you know well you have to be careful
about the hype here I mean you know
remember remember that that sort of holy
grail you know
goal you specify the business behavior
and it just executes well I you know a
little closer to that when you can
specify the Orcas account the way that
you specify the orchestration of these
services you actually specify a business
process model business process model and
then there's a generator that generates
that orchestration code that gets you a
little closer except those the business
process modest not really all the way
there to that ultimate goal is because
the models
that the business process models that
are amenable to being generated you can
generate that kind of stuff won't have
to be extremely precise and they're not
the kind that the average business
person is just going to you know sit
down and write yeah so it's interesting
so you've been talking about the
business process execution language and
many more around that all of these being
new format the kind of new
specifications new languages so no UML
no process modeling dsls derived or
profiles from your mouth where they at
least any learning source by any lineage
or is it really just we're starting over
again oh well I think that they're you
know I don't think there's only a
certain class of problems today that we
can attack by modeling a business
process model and having an executed
planned execution engine there are so
many classes of problems that the
majority we're still have to model an
application and you will know there's a
muse for that for sure so you know
there's just a month to go to utilities
it could be useful modeling the app and
then so it's right in some cases it is I
mean there it just depends where you
look there are there are a few you can
go to the oMG Institute eat some of the
work that people are doing the people
are working on standards they are
generally there they're working on it in
their industrial work so the there is a
fair amount of it going on but still the
average development project is still
done but is still done mo there's an
awful lot of low level coding but you
can see it you can see it in if you look
across industry though raising the level
of abstraction is there and then I
always be with you will now they like
people have their homegrown tools
different big companies might have their
own modeling languages but you know more
on you know and you see the hybrid model
and there isn't an X or both thing
happening it you may need extra
specification
languages for making existing
specification language system are
interoperable yeah okay well I mean
that's one of the purposes of having an
author well that's how the purposes of
having a standardized meta modeling
language that's why you want to have
that so that if you you you have to have
you mean you do need different languages
for different stakeholders have
different perspectives on your systems
they can't have the exact same set of
abstractions I didn't realize that I
were you saying that moth plays a role
for the web services standardization
efforts no they really hasn't but it
doesn't MDA is the core of the MDA stack
and I'm just saying that to the extent
that you have a common meta modeling
language it helps well now if you look
at the IBM stack I mean IBM the way they
implement a lot of their stuff they use
EMF the Eclipse modeling framework which
is essentially an implementation of
Mothe so they use it as a common data
modeling language for and and they used
for other stuff including the Revit you
know including the web service
implementation so maybe before we do you
want to say some more words about about
the web services specification efforts
Angela before we and Frank let you draw
draw a picture of mdaa where you think
we all should be going
they've got it's it's gotten to be a
very complex stack so why do they call
it so they call sometimes they call it
WS best bar sometimes achromatic WS yeah
Splatt or something yes bad okay no I
only something I only hear the phrase
like WS Death Star which just kind of I
guess a bit unfriendly from a Star Wars
but the point being it is very turning
into a very complex
yeah well I think that I myself have not
played a strong role in defining those
web services specs and so you know I
don't want to criticize my colleagues I
mean there are complex problems to be
solved I you know somebody I mean but if
you look at the size of the comparable
corpus stack I don't know I mean it's a
lot smaller this the size of the
specifications are a lot smaller now
that's a very high level comment and it
may be unfair okay no but I'll just
leave it at that
all right so maybe maybe to chop back to
MVA so maybe you want to give us an
overview of where you are today what
you're working on where you think we
should be going well one of the things
that I wrote quite a bit about and spoke
about when I was introducing was one of
the people that was introducing MDA to
the industry in the earlier part of this
decade and I predicted a certain area of
we're raising the level abstraction
would give us a very one of the most
useful paybacks and that I thought would
happen and most quickly and that was in
the data integration data mapping so the
classic problem that integration Alice
has they've got this data format or
message format and this other one and
they have to map them it's just enormous
amounts of IT resources go into solving
those problems there's all sorts of
legacy systems around you can't unplug
is too expensive to replace these
systems and you have to do all these
translations across industry across the
economy I've seen an economic economic a
kind of metric studies that show credit
it really sits a surprising amount of
impact overall on the probably
from this the amount of resources
expended on that problem and what week
and what I thought we would be able to
do and that or MDA languages for but you
know whether it was going to be with an
MDA language or some other you know non
you know standard language it seemed to
me that we ought to you know we were
getting to the point where we could
raise the level of abstraction where
instead of writing low-level code for
every one of those mappings you you
could present the integration analyst
with it with a mapping tool and so they
you know there's lots of these out there
you put the integration analyst in front
of a big in front of a big screen and
they have the two formats down the one
side of the screen you know one side of
the left side of the screen they see the
one format the right side of screen to
see other four on that they draw lines
between the between different from in
from one field on the left side to a
field on the right side they attach
expressions to those lines and the code
is generated or else it's executed on
the fly today there are all sorts of
integration tools out there that do that
and do it very effectively so we we did
make we've succeeded maybe not always
with MDA
you know tools based on the MDA stack
but in principle we succeeded in making
that in making that leap now there's a
now however in doing that we've solved
maybe 20% of the problem of the for the
integration analyst so what we what we
what we've accomplished is once the
integration analyst has decided what the
mapping should be it's relatively easy
compared to way it used to be for them
to specify that mapping and they don't
have to write a lot of low-level code
and they can do it with you know
and and and they don't have to you know
get bogged down in the mechanics of how
to actually execute them happen and
that's a genuine advance but we still
these tools give the integration analyst
absolutely no help in deciding what that
mapping should be okay so once they've
decided what it should be okay okay it
seemed much easier to actually execute
okay and that's where you know semantic
interoperability comes into play and
I've been doing this where I've been
doing quite a bit of work and that's in
in my world in in my in standards and
also in inside the company that I work
for we we have been we've made some real
advances there so you're you you
basically all the metadata all of a
series of obey the data that we have
about these from these schemas is purely
syntactical getting back to syntax
versus the semantics it's all some
tactical metadata yeah and the fact that
we have the syntactical metadata is what
allows the kinds of tools I just
described you know that generate code to
function so that's it so okay we need
that syntactic metadata yeah it
describes the type the format's okay but
there's absolutely no machine readable
semantic metadata so there's nothing for
a tool to grab onto to give a analyst
some guidance they have no underlying
semantic information about these data
elements and to give the semantics to
give the integration analyst some
guidance and we don't do the
econometrics studies that have been done
on the cross of data integration tell us
that we don't have to perform magic here
we don't have to magically create some
kind of super intelligent machine that
can automatically do these methods okay
if we can improve by helpful you know
suggestions with with with analysts
always having the override or you know
telling them they may have done
something wrong
you know if we can improve their
productivity by 30% the economic return
is enormous
yeah enormous okay so and I think we can
say that now we were making some real
progress there and the basic the basic
way this is approached and you see it
some of us some of the people who are
listening this may have heard of core
components for UNC fact that they've
done some of the basic work it's based
on the it's kind of concretization of an
earlier standard called I told one 1179
part five in particular and they they
actually have constructed a grammar for
a dated for a data element yeah the
basic grammar so just like okay we think
about we have in just the English
language we have a dictionary full of
words now those words are assembled into
sentences now I mean we called it
sentence diagramming in the US when I
was studying grammar when I was child
they would have us break down the scent
we'd look at a sentence we say what is
the subject where's this word is playing
the role of subject in this sentence
this word is playing the role of direct
object this word is playing the role of
indirect object so through these certain
roles that the words in your dictionary
assume in the context of this sentence
similarly what these this technology
I've just been describing does is it
finds you have a controlled vocabulary
of terms with information in there about
what what things are synonyms
synonyms what are Hamas and now you have
a grammar for a data element has you've
got underlying metadata that tells you
what is the there's a role that a term
can play not necessarily the name
there's a role that it can play there's
property term representation term you
know property qualify there's a various
roles that these terms can play and what
we're starting to do is with new specs
and even retrospectively going up and
marking up old specs with with semantic
metadata that says
this data element has a concept as this
thing as a concept this is his proper
term or this is his representation term
representations return for example is a
very high-level data kind of data types
as well it's it's an identifier or it's
a code or it's a name I'm not sure if
fully followed so when you typically
controlled vocabulary that's a use it in
the medical domain because you want to
make it possible for non IT people with
some with some foreigners of thinking to
express sentences which effectively are
specifications
so the controlled vocabulary you're
talking about is a meta vocabulary to
annotate existing specifications or
vocabulary you use tomorrow new domains
it can be used for both I mean it you
would have things like I mean I've
worked in the financial services domain
that's my primary domain I work in and
you know that you think you have things
you'll have things like checking account
in there usually you wouldn't define
account as an atomic term it's just too
it's too general you don't even define
checking account though it is there but
then you might and then you you would
have a balance and you would have code
identify or name things like that and
then when the data element you can say
there's prescribed rules just like in a
sentence we have the role of the direct
object the role of an indirect object or
prescribed roles at those play
conceptually in the data element and
that can be used so here's a classic
error that people who can't put into
this kind of stuff like this is a good
example of an error that integration
analyst can make so in one branch of the
military service this is a this is
actually sort of more from a defense
domain than a finance domain but in one
branch of the military a tank is a
military vehicle in another branch of
the military service a tank is a fuel
container so the analyst has got this
okay they got our modern mapping tools
up there
on the left side they see tank in this
field they see tank on the right side
they see tank you somewhere in there and
they draw the line
now that happens and those are subtle
errors that can take enormous resources
to to hunt down and cost a lot of money
now I'm not saying that our techniques
remember I said you don't have to have a
man to have magic here but you know if
you have a control vocab
these you know there's some they're
lying semantic metadata that says tank
here tank here these are and the tool
set that the mapping tool says well
these are actually two separate entries
in the dictionary but a homonym
relationship between them
you know analyst you may want to
reconsider that why you just drew
they're right yeah okay because they're
both yes they're both used as your
property term here but they're what if
you already have in your dictionaries
these are two different jobs its monthly
how about if you have a specification of
these terms independently of each other
your two specification matching well
that suggests there's a fair amount of
work still to be done
I had a related question maybe I
shouldn't well I'm really curious so
because you went back to integration
scenarios so I read this is a recurring
topic and there's nothing wrong with
that no it's not even a low-hanging
fruit it's done a huge amount of rock
but maybe it's the closest food we can
get to here and develop a silicon valley
for me the question is what does a
start-up do and they just don't use
don't use this tool so maybe as far as I
know they don't really use a lot of MBA
tools maybe because they can create the
homogeneous world right from the
beginning they take established
technology stacks and then they develop
that 10% additional
applications on top of that if you were
to make a very long shot at even
startups people and a significant
pressure but who are able to put so many
constraints into the ground that are not
given from the outside world they can
still choose what technology stack they
take etc so they make sure they have a
homogeneous world when would they
benefit from MDA and how could they use
it what needs to happen for that sort of
be a viable option for a start-up once
again I think we have to answer that
question I'm going to distinguish
between mga the brand names the
particular technology stack from the OMG
as opposed to the general concept of
raising the level of abstraction and
there I think there's there's a lot to
convene and you see it in different ways
I mean there's so many tools out there
that in some form or another raise the
level of abstraction for you I mean even
what we don't consider we don't normally
consider knowledge of in tools
you start off a new project to build a
new component and they they but they
bring up a dialogue and they ask you to
say well you want to use being you want
to use being managed persistence or do
you want to use this they ask you and
maybe even higher-level questions that
they ask you a lot of questions you
feeling right now radio buttons
checkboxes all sorts of options they
generate a nice starter code and I want
the real difference when I say
something's really model driven is when
that is not your last view of that
picture
because that's essentially in a sense of
abstraction of certain aspects of the
architecture of your system if that
picture can be recalled if you adjust it
okay yeah and you've got the you've got
it integrated you're really doing that
whether you're using UML whether you're
using a graphical language a textual
language a form space language you're
raising a level abstraction in a way
that supports iterative develop your
basic level abstraction you don't
support every move develop
that it's not practical right so you
know I I don't want to be dogmatic about
this I mean there are many ways to
approach this there are certain
advantages to following standards you
know I mean if you if you want to use a
form based interface but you know
certain advantages to defining your
underlying metamodel using some of the
standards mafia and that things like
that because then it's easier people to
integrate your stuff into their into
their stuff okay
so I think that that's the way I would
look at it so yeah I mean you ultimately
you're just trying to make people more
productive yep
I'm at the end of my questions so do you
have something that you would like to
say that we didn't touch on it yet well
the only thing I want to mention is that
you when I talked about that some of the
semantic interoperability work going on
I just wanted to point out that this was
yeah there is still more work to be done
however I want to point out that it's
more than just an idea at this point so
there are there is major implementation
work going on around this and a number
of different segments of industry now
and I think you're going to start to see
the emergence of a new class of tools
they're gonna be pretty interesting I
don't think they will saw I think
they'll get better
I think the techniques for how we go
back and retrospectively markup metadata
we're gonna we're gonna we have some
learning to do about that but I just
wanted to point out was it it's more
than on the drawing board
but yes there's still work to do so yeah
I just I just think we're we're we're on
a quest to make things be to be more
productive and more accurate yeah and
more reliable and that that's really to
go excellent thank you so much we will
put more information about David Frank
and maybe some pointers offer to look at
your work and to other show notes so
that's it from the Silicon Valley for
soft engineering radio thanks everyone
and goodbye thanks David thank you
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to
software engineering radio software
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website at s e -
radio dotnet if you want to support us
you can donate to the SE radio team via
the website or you can advertise press
your radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and Slashdot
buttons to contact the team please send
email to team at s e - radio net or if
it is specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under
Creative Commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the Passaic Music
Network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
travel
[Music]
you